Alexander E. Macdonald Papers,
Alexander E. Macdonald Papers and Photographs
1865-1906
Alexander E. Macdonald
10 linear feet; 8 boxes
Mss.arc
New York Academy of Medicine Library. Malloch Rare Book Room.
Alexander E. Macdonald (1845-1906), LL.B., M.D., was a Fellow of the New York Academy of Medicine and a prominent New York psychiatrist. Born in Toronto, Dr. Macdonald was educated at the Toronto Model Grammar School and at Upper Canada College. Although he began his medical studies at the University of Toronto, Dr. Macdonald moved to New York and ultimately received degrees in both medicine (M.D.) and law (LL. B.) from the University of the City of New York (now New York University) in 1870 and 1881, respectively.
Upon graduation from medical school, Dr. Macdonald was appointed assistant physician (and, later, resident physician) at the Hospital for Epileptics and Paralytics, Blackwell's Island, in 1870. The next year he became chief of staff of the Charity and Allied Hospitals, Blackwell's Island. In 1874, Dr. Macdonald began his long tenure at the New York City Asylum for the Insane, Ward's Island (later renamed the Manhattan State Hospital East), first as resident physician and then, from 1875 to 1904, as medical superintendent. In 1886, Dr. Macdonald became general superintendent of the New York City Asylums. This position brought with it responsibility for the administration not only of the New York City Asylum, Ward's Island (with its branches on Randall's Island and in Central Islip, Long Island), but also of the Reception Pavilion of the Insane, Bellevue and the New York City Lunatic Asylum, Blackwell's Island (with branches on Ward's and Hart's Island).
Notable achievements during Dr. Macdonald's career include his frequent consultation as an expert witness in important trials including the Guiteau, Rhinelander and Stokes cases as well as his work in the care of the tubercular insane, and the introduction of tent life for their treatment. Dr. Macdonald published widely and was a member of a number of medical organizations including not only the New York Academy of Medicine but also the American Medical Association, the Medical Society of the State of New York, the Medical Society of the County of New York, and the New York Psychiatrical Society. He was an honorary member of both the American Medico-Psychological Association (for which he served as President in 1904) and the British Medico-Psychological Association. Dr. Macdonald was routinely sent as a delegate of these organizations to various congresses and association meetings. In addition to his professional affiliations, Dr. Macdonald was a member of the Lotus Club and a Mason of Holland Lodge, New York City.
Over the course of his career, Dr. Macdonald held a number of academic posts. In 1874, he was appointed lecturer on Medical Jurisprudence at New York University. Subsequently, he became Professor of Psychological Medicine and Medical Jurisprudence, and was Emeritus Professor at NYU at the time of his death.
Alexander E. Macdonald was married to Elizabeth Woodbury Barrett (of Portland, Maine) on July 10, 1883. Together they had two children -- a son, Charles, and a daughter, Evelyn. Dr. Macdonald died on December 7, 1906.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the catalog of The New York Academy of Medicine Library. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
New York (City). Asylum for the Insane, Ward's Island.; New York (State). Board of Social Welfare.; Manhattan Psychiatric Center -- History -- 19th century.; Asylums -- New York (State) -- 19th century.; Medicine -- New York (State) -- New York -- 19th century.; Tuberculosis -- Treatment.; New York (City) Lunatic asylum, Blackwells Island.; Manhattan State Hospital; New York City Asylum for the Insane (Central Islip, N.Y.); New York University; University of the City of New York
Container List
- Business Records, Series I
  Scope and Content
  Business Records contains material generated during Dr. Macdonald's tenure as medical superintendent at the New York City Asylum for the Insane, Ward's Island, and general superintendent of the New York City Asylums. The series is divided into four subseries including: (a) Correspondence covering a wide range of institutional issues including, but not limited to, the purchase of goods and services; billing and account disputes; salary, wage and labor issues; construction and upkeep of building facilities; asylum conditions, practices and policies; inmate concerns; association and committee work; conference attendance; and legal issues; (b) Memoranda generated during the course of business on various topics including supplies; salaries and wages; and building facilities; (c) Asset Inventories for both the hospital and superintendent's residence; (d) Purchasing Records relating to the institutional acquisition of various goods and services; and (e) Other documentation including an architectural drawing and blueprint of building plans from Ward's Island.
  - Correspondence, Subseries A
    Arrangement
    Arranged chronologically.
    - Correspondence, 1868-1894; includes a letter to A.E. Macdonald from the family physician of William Magear "Boss" Tweed, 1873, on Tweed stationary (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, Jan-Dec, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, Jan-Dec, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, Jan-Apr, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, May-Nov, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, Dec 1897 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, Jan-June, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, July-Dec, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, Jan-Mar, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, Apr-Jun, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, Jul 1899 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, Aug-Sep, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, Oct-Dec, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, Jan-Jun, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, Jul-Dec, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, Jan-Dec, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, Jan-Dec, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, Jan-Jun, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, Jul-Dec, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, Jan-Jun, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, Jul-Dec, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence, Jan-Jun, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, Jul-Dec, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence, Jan-Dec, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence, Jan-Dec, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Memoranda, Subseries B
    - State of New York - Manhattan State Hospital. Momoranda for Board meeting, or meeting of the Finance Committee..., 1896 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - State of New York - State Commission in Lunacy. Coffee memorandum, [1897?] (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - State of New York - Manhattan State Hospital, Central Islip. Memorandum. In the matter of the "Trojan" gravity heaters: --..., 1899 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - State of New York - Manhattan State Hospital. Memorandum: -- from Dr. Smith. Mr. Heins visited the farm Sunday forenoon,..., 1899 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Manhattan State Hospital, Central Islip. Memorandum. We had canned corn and succotash..., 1899 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - State of New York - Manhattan State Hospital, Central Islip. Memorandum. Comments on notes of the official visit of the State Commission in Lunacy..., 1899 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - State of New York - Manhattan State Hospital, Central Islip. Memorandum. In the matter of reduction in salaries and wages..., 1899 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - State of New York - State Commission in Lunacy. Memoranda of conference between General Superintendent of Manhattan State Hospital and the State Commission in Lunacy..., 1899 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Memorandum for Mr. Dodge to report to the Board..., 1901 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - State of New York - Manhattan State Hospital, East. Ward's Island, New York City. Memorandum: Dr. Pettit will please mark on the history of the patient Morawaki..., 1903 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - State of New York - Manhattan State Hospital, East. Ward's Island, New York City. Memorandum: The Resident Steward will please report in writing..., 1903 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Memorandum of Mr. Sussdorff's visit, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - State of New York - State Commission in Lunacy. Manhattan State Hospital. Memorandum. Names of firms to whom proposals may be sent inviting bids for supplies:..., undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Memorandum. Mr. Cole: Railroad tickets..., undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - State of New York - State Commission in Lunacy. Tea memorandum, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Memoranda as a result of Commission's visit, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Memoranda. Estimate regarding the cost of the use of hard, soft, and pea coal, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Central Islip. Data regarding soft coal, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Memorandum: Cost of erecting and twice renewing 27" smoke stack..., undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Assett Inventories, Subseries C
    - Inventory, Manhattan State Hospital, East. September 30, 1903. Superintendent's Residence (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - List of articles donated to the M. S. H. East, by Dr. A.E. Macdonald..., 1903; 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Inventory, Manhattan State Hospital, East. September 30, 1904. Superintendent's Residence (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Purchasing Records (Goods and Services), Subseries D
    - Documents pertaining to the purchase of goods (including clothing, food, office, cleaning and medical supplies, kitchen equipment, furniture, fuel, etcetera) and services (including wages, salaries and other labor) for several institutions (some unidentified and undated), 1897-1906 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Other, Subseries E
    - Miscellaneous business records, 1890-1904 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Items pertaining to Manhattan State Hospital Exhibit at the Universal Exposition, St. Louis, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous business records, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous business records, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Blueprint of Ward's Island Coffee Roasting Plant, 1897 (Box 8)
    - Architectural drawing on sized linen depicting grounds and administrative building of unidentified institution, undated (Box 8)
- Printed Material, Series II
  Printed Material includes (a) Annual Reports from the Department of Public Charities and Correction, the Manhattan State Hospital and the State Commissioner in Lunacy; (b) Journal Reprints, including among other items a number of articles authored by Dr. Macdonald that appeared in the American Journal of Insanity; (c) Minutes of meetings of the Commissioners of Public Charities and Correction, the Medical Society of the County of New York and the State Commission in Lunacy; and (d) Other publications including articles; lectures; reports; asylum rules, regulations and directories.
  - Annual Reports, Subseries A
    Arranged in subseries by author.
    - Department of Public Charities and Correction, Subseries 1
      Arranged chronologically
      - Annual report of the Medical Superintendent of the N.Y. City Asylum for Insane, Ward;s Island, N.Y., for the year 1875 (Box 3, Envelope 1)
      - Annual report of the Resident Physician of the New York City Lunatic Asylum, Blackwell's Island, N.Y., for the year 1874, 1875 (Box 3, Envelope 2)
      - Annual report of the Chief of Staff of the Charity, Fever, Epileptic, Penitentiary, Alms House and Work House Hospitals, and Hospital for Incurables, Blackwell's Island, N.Y. for the year endind December 31, 1875, 1876 (Box 3, Envelope 3)
      - Annual report of the Medical Superintendent of the 1879 N.Y. City Asylum for Insane, Ward's Island, N.Y., for the year 1878 (Box 3, Envelope 4)
      - Annual report of the Medical Superintendent of the N.Y. City Asylum for Insane, Ward's Island, N.Y., for the year 1880 (Box 3, Envelope 5)
      - Annual report of the Medical Superintendent of the New York City Asylum for the Insane, for the year 1881, 1882 (Box 3, Envelope 6)
      - same, for the year 1882, 1885 (Box 3, Envelope 7)
      - same, for the year 1883 (Box 3, Envelope 8)
      - Annual report of the General Superintendent of the New York City Asylums for the Insane, for the year 1886, 1887 (Box 3, Envelope 9)
      - Annual report of the New York City Asylums for the Insane, for the year 1887, 1891 (Box 3, Envelope 10)
      - The New York City Asylums for the Insane. Extract from the Annual Report for 1890, "Overcrowding", 1891 (Box 3, Envelope 11)
      - Annual report of the General Superintendent of the New York City Asylums for the Insane, for the year 1892, 1895 (Box 3, Envelope 12)
      - Twenty-fourth annual report of the Commissioners of Public Charities and Correction, of the City of New York, for the year 1883, 1887 (Box 3, Wrapper 1)
      - Twenty-fifth annual report of the Commissioner's of Public Charities and Correction, of the City of New York, for the year 1884, [1887?] (Box 3, Wrapper 1)
      - Twenty-seventh annual report of the Commissioners of Public Charities and Correction, of the City of New York, for the year 1886, 1887 (Box 3, Wrapper 2)
      - Thirthieth annual report of the Commissioners of Public Charities and Correction of the City of New York, for the year 1889, 1892 (Box 3, Wrapper 3)
      - Annual report of the New York City Asylums for the Insane, for the year 1889, 1894 (Box 3, Wrapper 4)
      - Annual report of the New York City Asylums for the Insane, for the year 1893, 1895 (Box 3, Wrapper 5)
      - Annual report of the New York City Asylums for the Insane, for the year 1894, 1898 (Box 3, Wrapper 6)
    - Manhattan State Hospital, Subseries 2
      - Second annual report of the Managers of the Manhattan State Hospital at New York to the State Commission in lunacy for the year ending September 30, 1897, 1898 (Box 3, Envelope 1)
      - Third annual report of same for the year ending September 30, 1898, 1899 (Box 3, Envelope 2)
      - Fourth annual report of same for the year ending September 30, 1899, 1900 (Box 3, Envelope 3)
      - Fifth annual report of same for the year ending September 30, 1900, 1901 (Box 3, Envelope 4)
      - Sixth annual report of same for the year ending September 30, 1902 (Box 3, Envelope 5)
      - Eighth annual report of the Manhattan State Hospital at New Yorkto the State Commission in Lunacy for the year ending September 30, 1903, 1904 (Box 3, Envelope 6)
      - Ninth annual report of same for the year ending September 30, 1904, 1907 (Box 3, Envelope 7)
  - Journal Reprints, Subseries B
    - The practical working of the new lunacy statutes [reprinted from the Psychological and Medico-Legal Journal], 1875 (Box 3, Envelope 1)
    - Proceedings of the Association of Medical Superintendents of American Institutions for the Insane, at its twenty-ninth annual meeting, held at Auburn, N.Y., May 1875 [reprinted from the American Journal of Insanity], 1876 (Box 3, Envelope 2)
    - Macdonald, A.E. General paresis [reprinted from the American Journal of Insanity], 1877 (Box 3, Envelope 3)
    - Haviland, F.C. Tent life for the tuberculous insane [reprinted from the American Journal of Insanity], 1902 (Box 3, Envelope 4)
    - New York Conference of Charities, November 20 to 23, 1901. Report of Committee on the Mentally Defective [reprinted from the American Journal of Insanity], 1902 (Box 3, Envelope 5)
    - Macdonald, A.E. The Fourteenth International Medical Congress at Madrid. Report as delegate of the American Medico-Psychological Association [reprinted from the American Journal of Insanity], 1903 (Box 3, Envelope 6)
    - Macdonald, A.E. Presidential address [reprinted from the American Journal of Insanity], 1905 (Box 3, Envelope 7)
    - Rowe, J.T.W. The prevention of insanity in its Incubation by the general practitioner [reprinted from the New York Medical Journal and Philadelphia Medical Journal], 1905 (Box 3, Envelope 8)
    - Memorial Notice. Alexander E. Macdonald [reprinted from the Proceedings of the American Medico-Psychological Association], 1907; 2 copies (Box 3, Envelope 9)
    - Obituary. Alexander E. Macdonald [reprinted from American Journal of Insanity], 1907 (Box 3, Envelope 10)
    - Campbell, C.M. Untitled (memorial notice) with photo reproduction of Macdonald [reprinted from American Journal of Insanity], 1907; 2 copies (Box 3, Envelope 11)
  - Minutes, Subseries C
    - Minutes. Meeting of the Commissioners of Public Charities and Correction, 1870 (Box 3, Envelope 1)
    - Minutes. Meeting of the Commissioners of Public Charities and Correction, 1872 (Box 3, Envelope 2)
    - Minutes of the Medical Society of the County of New York. Stated Meeting, May 27, 1878 (Box 3, Envelope 3)
    - Minutes of the Medical Society of the County of New York. Special Meeting, Sept. 3, 1878 (Box 3, Envelope 3)
    - Medico-Legal Society of New York. Meeting, April 10, 1889 (Box 3, Envelope 4)
    - State of New York - State Commission in Lunacy. State Hospitals -- December and January Estimates 1898-1899. Abstract of minutes and resolutions... (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - State of New York - State Commission in Lunacy. State Hospitals - April and May Estimates - 1899. Abstract of minutes and resolutions (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - State of New York - State Commission in Lunacy. State Hospitals - June and July Estimates - 1899. Abstract of minutes and resolutions (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - State of New York - State Commission in Lunacy. State Hospitals - August and September Estimates - 1899. Abstract of minutes and resolutions (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - State of New York - State Commission in Lunacy. Notes of Conference..., 1905 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Other, Subseries D
    - Macdonald, A.E. A lecture delivered before the pupils of the School for Nurses, Charity Hospital, N.Y., October 6, 1875, on the nursing of the insane (Box 3, Envelope 1)
    - The American Psychological Journal, Vol. 3, No. 3, 1876 (Box 3, Envelope 2)
    - Fifth annual reunion dinner of the Alumni Medical Department of the University of the City of New York, 1876 (Box 3, Envelope 3)
    - Report of the Committee on Public Health relative to lunatic asylums, 1879 (Box 3, Envelope 4)
    - The answer of the New York Neurological Society to the Document known as the Report of the Committee on Public Health Relative to Lunatic Asylums, {Nr. 64, In Senate, May 22, 1879}, 1880 (Box 3, Envelope 5)
    - Report of the proceedings for establishing a Board of Commissioners in Lunacy, for the State of New York. Supervision of our Asylums for the Insane, 1880 (Box 3, Envelope 6)
    - Report on the insane and lunatic asylums of New York City, 1883 (Box 3, Envelope 7)
    - State of New York. Report of the Senate Committee on Finance relative to the value of the land and buildings, 1891 (Box 3, Envelope 8)
    - State Charities Aid Assn. of N.Y. Report of the Special Committee on the Division of the Department of Public Charities and Correction of New York City [reprinted from the Twenty-Third Annual Report of the State Charities Aid Association to the State Board of Charities], 1895 (Box 3, Envelope 9)
    - Protestant Chapels. Order of Services, 1897 (Box 3, Envelope 10)
    - Protestant Chapels. Selection of hymns and psalms, 1897 (Box 3, Envelope 11)
    - State of New York, State Commission in Lunacy, official directory of state hospitals and private institutions for the insane, 1903 (Box 3, Envelope 12)
    - Macdonald, A.E. Tent treatment for tuberculous insane, 1904 (Box 3, Envelope 13)
    - State of New York. No. 416, 906, 2426. Int. 400. IN Assembly, January 26, 1899. An Act making appropriations for the support of government (Box 3, Envelope 14)
    - State of New York. No. 1745, 2454. Int. 1327. In Assembly, April 24, 1899. An Act making appropriations for certain expenses of government.... (Box 3, Envelope 14)
    - State of New York. No. 2455. Int. 1624. In Assembly, April 28, 1899. An Act making an appropriation of certain expenses of government.... (Box 3, Envelope 14)
    - State of New York. No. 544. Int. 496. In Assembly, February 9, 1905. An Act to amend the insanity law.... (Box 3, Envelope 14)
    - No. 82. State Charities Aid Association of New York. A consideration of the arguments contained in the memorandum filed by Governor Odell in approving the bill abolishing the Boards of Managers of the State Hospitals for the Insane, 1902 (Box 3, Envelope 15)
    - Marro, A. Il trattamento degli alienate sotto tenda nel Manicomio governativo di Manhattan in America, 1906 (Box 3, Envelope 16)
    - New York City Asylum for the Insane, Ward's Island. Description of the plan, arrangement and capacity, undated (Box 3, Envelope 17)
    - Duties of attendats at the New York City Asylum for the Insane, Ward's Island, undated (Box 3, Envelope 17)
    - Extracts from the Rules and Regulations of the Manhattan State Hospital, undated (Box 3, Envelope 17)
    - By-laws of the Congress of American Physicians and Surgeons, undated (Box 3, Envelope 17)
    - Kinney, A.C. Tuberculosis: History of teh cure of a desperate case with immunity treatment, undated (Box 3, Envelope 17)
    - Memorandum Filed by Governor Odell in Approving Assembly Bill Number 438...., undated (Box 3, Envelope 17)
    - Collection of A.E. Macdonald's student course and hospital tickets, various; 12 items (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous printed material including documents published by the State Commission in Lunacy, various printed ephemera, 1904 card-backed Calendar from Manhattan State Hospital, East, etc... (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Professional Material, Series III
  Professional Material is comprised of three subseries: (a) Legal Documents which include briefs, transcripts of testimony and arguments, court orders and correspondence in a number of cases including, most notably, the Guiteau, Rhinelander and Stokes Will cases as well as the Investigation into the Management and Affairs of the New York City Insane Asylum, Ward's Island; (b) Memberships and Medical Conferences which include documentation pertaining to Dr. Macdonald's membership in various professional medical organizations and a range of correspondence, programs, newspaper clippings and ephemera related to his attendance of various medical conferences, including the 12th International Medical Congress in Moscow (1897), the British Medical Association Session in Edinburgh (1898), the 14th International Medical Congress in Madrid, Spain (1903) and the 15th International Medical Congress in Lisbon, Portugal (1906); and (c) Other material pertaining to Dr. Macdonald's professional endeavors including a collection of course tickets and curriculum announcements from the University of the City of New York.
  - Legal Documents, Subseries A
    Arranged in subsubseries by case name.
    - Charles Guiteau Trial, Subsubseries 1
      - Ticket to trial, 1881 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Signature of Charles Guiteau, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - In the matter of the application of Mary W.B. Mariotte for sale real estate of infants, Subsubseries 2
      - Affidavit and Order for Discharge of Special Guardian (petitioner), 1895 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence from M. Winslow (counsel for petitioner), 1894-1895 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence from Barrett [illegible?], 1894 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - In the matter of the investigation of the New York City Asylums, Subsubseries 3
      - Correspondence to A.E. Macdonald from G.F. Britton, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence to H. Porter from A.E. Macdonald, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence to A.E. Macdonald from A. Phillips, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence to H. Porter from unidentified (incomplete), 1894 (Box 4, Folder 1)